Guide to the John Archiquette Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Archiquette collection
1817-1984
1876-1919
WA MSS S-2662
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.04
(3 boxes) + 3 broadside folders
This collection chiefly consists of professional and personal papers of John Archiquette that document events and activities of the Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin, primarily between 1876-1919. It also contains materials collected by his heirs, 1866-1984. The personal papers include ledger volumes that Archiquette used as journals and letter books, which include brief and frequent entries related to community affairs and events, as well as to his personal life and family. The collection also includes records of the Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin kept by Joseph O. Powless and Archiquette, which principally document deaths in the community, 1817-1880, as well as the records of the vestry council of the Church of the Holy Apostles in Oneida, Wisconsin, kept by Peter Bread and Archiquette, 1881-1906.
Archiquette, John, 1847-1923
Bread, Peter, b. 1845
Powless, Joseph O., d. 1868
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from John Cato on the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
John Archiquette (1847-1923)
John Archiquette (1847-1923) was a prominent member of the Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin. He was a veteran of the American Civil War; a captain of the Oneida Indian police force; a vestryman and warden of the Church of the Holy Apostles in Oneida, Wisconsin; and a member of the Oneida National Brass Band.
Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin
The Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin is a sovereign nation comprised of Oneida Indians who relocated from central New York state to eastern Wisconsin in and around Green Bay from 1823 to 1841.
Holy Apostles Episcopal Church in Oneida, Wisconsin
The Holy Apostles Episcopal Church in Oneida, Wisconsin, is a mission congregation of the Episcopal Diocese of Fond du Lac founded in 1825. The church was originally named Hobart Episcopal Church for John Henry Hobart (1775-1830), the third Episcopal bishop of New York (1816-1830).
Scope and Contents
This collection chiefly consists of professional and personal papers of John Archiquette that document events and activities of the Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin, primarily between 1876-1919. It also contains materials collected by his heirs, 1866-1984. The personal papers include ledger volumes that Archiquette used as journals and letter books, which include brief and frequent entries related to community affairs and events, as well as to his personal life and family. The collection also includes records of the Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin kept by Joseph O. Powless and Archiquette, which principally document deaths in the community, 1817-1880, as well as the records of the vestry council of the Church of the Holy Apostles in Oneida, Wisconsin, kept by Peter Bread and Archiquette, 1881-1906.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Personal Papers, 1866-1984. II. Records of the Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin, 1817-1866. III. Records of the Church of the Holy Apostles, Oneida, Wisconsin, 1881-1905.
Church records and registers -- Wisconsin -- Oneida; Episcopal Church -- Wisconsin -- Oneida; Indians of North America -- Wisconsin; Oneida Indians; Registers of births, etc. -- Wisconsin -- Oneida Reservation; Oneida (Wis.); Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin; Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin -- Religion; Church records; Diaries; Archiquette, John, 1847-1923; Bread, Peter, b. 1845; Powless, Joseph O., d. 1868; Holy Apostles Episcopal Church (Oneida, Wis.)
- Personal Papers, 1866-1984; Series I; 72
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into four subseries: Diaries and Letter Books, Logs, Correspondence, Notes, and Collected Materials.
  Scope and Contents
  This series chiefly consists of volumes kept by John Archiquette, as well as logs, correspondence, and materials collected by Archiquette and his heirs that document events and activities at the reservation of the Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin.
  - Diaries and Letter Books
    Arranged chronologically.
    Diaries and letter books kept in ledger books by Archiquette that document events and activities at the Oneida Nation of Wisconsin.
    The first six volumes include manuscript transcriptions of his monthly reports to the Indian agent in his role as the head of the police force on the Indian reservation, 1876-1901. The monthly reports includes logs of life events, including births, marriages, and deaths, as well as descriptions of legal infractions on tribal land, such as cutting timber without a permit, and social transgressions, such as adultery. The volumes include transcriptions of other official and personal correspondence by Archiquette.
    The last two volumes were kept by Archiquette during his retirement, 1906-1919, The volumes include logs of life events, as well as records of his daily activities and transcriptions of his personal correspondence. There is also a fragment from a volume, which documents his activities in September and October 1910, as well as his financial disbursements in March 1910.
    - Volume, 1876-1882 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Volume, 1882-1885 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Includes a transcription of a letter from Hiram Price (1814-1901), Commissioner of Indian Affairs, to Ebenezer Stephens (born circa 1835), who administered the Green Bay Agency, 1879-1882. The letter outlines provisos of the Oneida Treaty of 1838 (7 Stat. 566, Feb. 3, 1838).
      Includes a transcription of the rules and regulations of the United States Indian Police Service in July 1878.
      Includes transcriptions of personal correspondence, including letters to his children, Joel B. Archiquette (1870-1905) and Belinda Archiquette (1872-1910) while they attended the Carlisle Indian Industrial School.
    - Volume, 1886-1890 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Volume, 1890-1894 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Includes a manuscript map of a strip of land adjoining his property that Archiquette purchased from his neighbor Thomas John, Sr., in 1890-1892.
    - Volume, 1896-1899 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Volume, 1898-1901 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Volume, 1906-1910 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Volume fragment, 1910 March-October (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Volume, 1916-1919 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Logs
    - Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin Bylaws, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Log of Events, 1868 September-December (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Log of Births, 1868 September-1875 May (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Log of Marriages, 1868 October-1976 June (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Log of Events, 1869 January-1874 March (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Log of Marriages, 1872-1879 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Log of Weather, 1908-1916 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Log of Visitors, 1916 February-May (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence
    - Archiquette, John to Stephens, Ebenezer, 1880 October 30 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Archiquette, John to Ferguson, Edward, 1882 April 12 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Goodenough, Edward A. to Archiquette, Martin D., 1887 July 25 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Belt, Robert V. to Lamb, Dana C, 1889 November 7 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Archiquette, John to Morgan, Thomas Jefferson, 1890 March 29 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Archiquette, John to Savage, Thomas H., 1896 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - George, D. H. to Gegier, 1898 February 24 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - William Larsen Canning Company to Archiquette, John, 1902 October 10 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Archiquette, John to United States Commissioner of Pensions, 1903 June 3 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Archiquette, John to Currie Brothers Company, 1904 April 2 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Archiquette, John to Strehlow, Max H., 1904 July 22 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Archiquette, John to Hart, Joseph C., 1905 June 19 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Wisconsin County Court (Brown County) to Archiquette, John, 1905 June 23 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Archiquette, John to Buell, C. E., 1905 June 24 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Archiquette, Irene to Smith, Christine Archiquette Webster, circa 1905 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Envelope only
    - United States Department of the Interior, United States Pension Agency to Archiquette, John, 1908 July 11 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Hill, Belinda Archiquette to Archiquette, John, 1910 March 11 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Archiquette, John to Hart, John C., 1910 August 2 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Burleson, Hugh Latimer to Archiquette, John, 1912 April 3 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Photographic postcard depicting John Ely Burleson (born 1911)
    - Pratt, Richard Henry to Archiquette, Martin D., 1915 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Archiquette, John to Archiquette, Martin D. or Chauncey, 1916 April 18. (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - United States Treasury Department, Liberty Loan Organization to Archiquette, John, 1918 September 26 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Bogle, Phyllis Winnifred Archiquette to Cato, Arbutus Bogle, 1951 February 19 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      Photocopy
    - Archiquette, Oscar to Summerfield, Arthur E., 1952 December 1 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Archiquette, Oscar to Bogle, Phyllis Winnifred Archiquette, 1961 January 5 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Archiquette, Oscar to Bogle, Phyllis Winnifred Archiquette, 1970 October 10 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - United States Department of the Interior, Bureau of Indian Affairs to Bogle, Phyllis Winnifred Archiquette, 1970 September 25 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Notes
    Arranged chronologically
    Notes chiefly by John Archiquette, except where noted, about Oneida families and other subjects.
    - Notes on the Families of Elijah Powless, Elisabeth Antone, and Thomas Schuyler, circa 1902 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Notes on Iroquois (Haudenosaunee) Population in 1901 and the Finances of the Church of the Holy Apostles, circa 1905 April (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Notes on the Green Family, 1909 January 19 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Notes on the Archiquette Family, circa 1909 May (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - List of Oneida Soldiers in World War I, circa 1918 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Oscar Archiquette, Notes on the State Historical Society fo Wisconsin, Newberry Library, and Museum of the American Indian, circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Phyllis Winnifred Archiquette Bogle, Notes on the Family of Christine Archiquette Webster Smith, 1970 October 13 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Collected Material
    - Adoption Notice of Isaac Cooper by Levi Parker and Mary Ann Parker, 1893 May 19 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Seating List, 1897 May 27 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Archiquette, John, "Is it Really Wicked to Dance", 1898 September 16 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Statement by Thomas Schuyler About Being Shot by Isaac Smith, 1902 May 7 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Newspaper Tear sheet, Melissa Green Training as a Nurse at Trinity Hospital, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, 1903 February 5 (Box bsd, folder 56)
    - Program for the 16th Reunion of the 14th Wisconsin Volunteer Infantry in New London, Wisconsin, 1903 June 16-18 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Roster of the Living Ex-Members of the 14th Wisconsin Veteran Volunteer Infantry, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Bill of Sale for Furniture from Hugh James and Lena James to Archiquette, John, 1911 August 2 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Agreement by Joseph Van Enkevert and Louis Van Gheem to Rent Pastureland from John Archiquette, 1911 November 13 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Newspaper Clipping, Society of American Indians Convention in Denver, Colorado, 1913 October 12 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Arrest of Laura Cornelius Kellogg and Orrin J. Kellogg, circa 1913 October (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Newspaper Clipping, Armenians in Turkey, 1917 December 19 (Box bsd, folder 63)
    - Monmouth Plow Factory, Circular, circa 1917 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Newspaper Clipping, Marriage of Leah Summers to Theodore Brunt in Aurora, Colorado, 1919 February 1 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Receipt from M. J. Maes of the State Bank, De Pere, Wisconsin, to John Archiquette, 1919 February 21 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Receipt from G. L. Morgan Grocery Store, Oneida, Wisconsin, to Oscar Archiquette, 1919 February 22 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Newspaper Clipping, Probate Notice for Christine Archiquette Webster Smith, 1958 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Leaflet, Oneida Industrial Park, circa 1965 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Transcription of an Obituary of Raymond Parkhurst, 1984 November 8 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Newspaper, The Fond du Lac Clarion, 1984 December (Box bsd, folder 71)
    - Manuscript fragments, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
- Records of the Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin, 1817-1880; Series II; 2
  This series consists of records related to the Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin kept by Joseph O. Powless (died 1868) and continued by John Archiquette. The records include a bound volume that documents deaths, 1817-1880, as well as information related to tribal finances, circa 1866
  - Log of Deaths, 1817 July-1880 November (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Tribal Finances, circa 1866 (Box 3, Folder 74)
- Records of the Vestry Council of the Church of the Holy Apostles, Oneida, Wisconsin, 1881-1905; Series III; 4
  This series consists of records for the vestry council of the Church of the Holy Apostles, Oneida, Wisconsin. The records include a volume of vestry council records, 1881-1906, as well as scattered meeting notes from 1882 and 1905.
  - Vestry Council Records, 1881 April 18-1906 April 16 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    The first portion of the volume consists of records and meeting notes for the vestry council kept by Peter Bread (born 1845), April 18, 1881, to March 28, 1888.
    The second portion of the volume consists of a log of work by individuals for the church, including quarrying stone, building structures, and preparing meals, April 24, 1882, to March 29, 1888.
    The third portion of the volume consists of scattered records and meeting notes for the vestry council kept by John Archiquette, June 23, 1890, to April 16, 1906.
  - Vestry Council Meeting Notes, 1882 May 8 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Vestry Council Meeting Notes, 1905 April 25 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Vestry Council Meeting Notes, 1905 October 2 (Box 3, Folder 78)